Hi, and welcome back to
another episode with ItsDrdan.
And today we're going
to be looking at gases.
So why so much on gases?
Well, the whole idea about this, this
particular subject is that gases are
one of the three major phases of matter.
So, and what makes them really
important is that unlike solids
and liquids, the molecules of gas,
they're spread really far apart.
And that means that
they have very minimal.
Intermolecular force interactions.
So there's really not a lot
of hydrogen bonding, not a lot
of dipole dipole dispersion.
So it makes it an ideal system
for chemists and physicists to
be able to study to see how does
the most simple molecules exist?
How do they behave with
one another when they?
interact with one another, especially
when you kind of compare these different
images that I prepared up here.
When you look at a solid, it's all
being held together very, very tightly.
Liquids are a little bit farther apart.
They have interactions.
It makes it extremely
complex to understand.
Gases are far apart.
It is a simpler system.
So, um, the big idea with these gases,
they move independently of one another.
They just bounce all over the place
like a bunch of billiard balls.
So what are some common examples of this?
How can I illustrate this for you?
Let's dive in.
So gases are all around us.
We see a lot of different common
gases, um, that you're going to come
across in chemical reactions and
trying to identify some of these.
There are a couple that are really quick
and easy to find on your periodic table.
Um, for example, the first,
the first few It's just when
you're looking at noble gases.
So that last column of the
periodic table They're starting
with helium down to xenon.
These are all that's in its name
noble gas Those are some of the
most common ones that you'll see.
You also have the diatomic gases.
An easy Mnemonic to remember the diatomic
gases is have no fear of ice cold beer.
So with that one It's H2, N2, F2, O2,
I2, Cl2, and Br2 for all the diatomics.
And a diatomic gas is that there's
always seven of them, so they're,
uh, with these seven gases, they
are always binding to themselves.
So they are a notorious seven,
they, you never, you'll always
see these seven together.
So whenever hydrogen is
produced as a product, it's
always going to be as H2 gas.
If oxygen is being produced as a
product, it's going to be O2 gas.
This is extremely important
for chemical reactions.
So I would recommend writing
those down for yourself because
you will see them be produced.
There are a lot of other common
molecular gases that we see
in our everyday lives too.
For example, you currently right now
are breathing, which I hope, right?
So you're breathing in air, which is
oxygen, nitrogen, the diatomics, and
what comes out of you when you exhale.
Well, things like CO2, for example,
um, you might, if you ever come across
some other gases, let's say if you
ever cook, you might use propane gas.
If you cook with a gas burner
at home, uh, there are a lot
of other gases I come across.
Like for example, with ammonia, sometimes
it's produced with cleaning products.
These are different.
Gases that we come across in
our regular everyday lives.
So it comes in molecular,
atomic, and diatomic form.
We see it all the time.
So how do we go about measuring these?
So when it comes to units of measurement,
so over here on the left hand side, there
are four major things that we're going
to be looking at when measuring them.
There's volume, temperature,
the amount, so moles.
and pressure.
So these are all things that are somehow
they can be actually looked at in the lab.
They are different things
that are measurable.
So volume, you could capture a
gas, you can measure the volume.
If you think of your tires,
for example, for your car, you
might measure the pressure.
of those tires to make sure that
they are at the right levels.
You can measure the temperature
of the room that you are
currently in to see, is it cold?
Is it hot?
These are going to affect the gases.
The amount or moles is how
much are you breathing in.
If you think of a balloon, for
example, and you start With
that balloon, it's empty, right?
There's no moles of gas in it.
But once you start blowing into it,
it gets bigger and bigger and bigger.
You are adding moles of gas to it.
That's one of the big ideas.
So with gases, they are all
around you right now, right?
There's a homogeneous mixture of gases
around you as you are sitting here.
You have oxygen, nitrogen, CO2,
all the gases all around you.
These gases, what they are
doing is they are exhibiting
a pressure on you as a result.
So that is atmospheric pressure,
meaning that all the gases on,
on earth are pushing down on you.
They are being pulled down
by gravity, meaning that.
As we are, if you were at sea level
right now, then the air is much denser
up here or down here versus if you
go up into the mountains, let's say
if you go above, if you start going
hiking and you go into like Yosemite
or Yellowstone or any of these national
parks, the mounds are really high.
It might get a little harder to breathe.
Yes, you might be doing some
cardio, but realistically the air
is a lot thinner too, and that's
because the atmospheric pressure.
Decreases as you go up.
So we're going to be using a
couple of different things as well.
That are some standards.
So yes, you have pressure and
volume and these different units,
but we, and for a lot of these,
when we're going to be looking at.
is when we are measuring them, we
want to stick into four common units.
You always want your volume to
be in liters, temperature to be
in Kelvin, moles and moles, and
the pressure for atmospheres, and
there's many different units that
can be used, but for these videos,
we're going to stick to these four.
Now, when it comes to standardized
pressure and temperature, so STP,
this is always referring to 273
Kelvin, so if you think of the Celsius
conversion term, And at one atmosphere
or 76 or 760 millimeters of mercury.
So why is that important?
Well, what, what does that mean?
What is pressure?
Well, when it comes to pressure,
the whole idea is that we take
something like a barometer, which
is over here on the left hand side.
Now, what is actually
happening here is that.
You have air pushing
against a liquid surface.
So if I have a dish here,
it is full of mercury.
Mercury is a metallic, a liquid metal.
Now, when air is pushing down
on the surface, it's causing...
The mercury in the tube
to stay inside of it.
Now, if the pressure is changing, if
there's like a rainstorm coming in or
a weather front changing, this level
here is going to change going up and
down just by little amounts, and that
all has to do with the atmospheric.
Pressure pushing against it.
So, gravity is pushing the
liquid down, and the atmospheric
pressure is trying to push it up.
So when that happens, the forces are
pushing against each other, which is
how we read our pressure every day.
So in lab, it might be really common
where you have to use a barometer to
try to do some simple conversions.
So how do we do these conversions?
Let's practice it.
So this is something that's a basic
dimensional analysis conversion.
So when you are going through
these, you're going to set up just
a little t table for yourself.
So, what we're given is it asks us
to convert 728 mmHg to atmospheres.
So, what we're gonna do is we're
gonna write down our given piece
of information, and we're gonna
illustrate that for ourselves.
So we have 728 mmHg.
And how do we convert that to atmospheres?
Well, for this one, the common
conversion is that 760 mmHg,
is equal to one atmosphere.
So how would we set this up?
Well, it's about cancelling units.
They have to be opposite of one another.
So we will put the 760 mmHg on the bottom.
That's going to cancel out.
One atmosphere is going to go on the top.
And that's going to help us
cancel that one out as well.
Now when you, or that's going to
leave us with our units that are left.
Now, when we go through this, what you're
gonna get, so you're gonna take 728,
divide it by 760 to get your final answer,
and you'll get a pretty big number.
You'll get 0.
95789.
Now, is that the right way to show it?
Well, we gotta count sig figs.
So, being that this 1 started with 1, 2, 3
sig figs, we gotta round it to 3 sig figs.
So, we'll round it to the third spot.
So it's gonna be nine five eight
atmospheres and that's gonna
be our answer for this one.
That's how you convert.
Let's do one more time for ourselves.
So if I want to convert 1.
27 millimeter, our atmospheres
to millimeters of mercury,
how would I do that?
Well, once again, we're gonna
illustrate, oops, we're gonna 1.
27 atmospheres.
And we're going to set that up
as well in a table for ourselves.
We're going to use the same conversions.
So in this case, we're going
to put atmospheres opposite.
So when we do that, we can set it up
where atmospheres cancels atmospheres.
And what we're going to have
is 760 millimeters of mercury.
It's leaving that unit for us.
Which is exactly what we want.
So we'll take 1.
27, times it by 760, and
what you are going to get is
965 millimeters of mercury.
That's your answer.
Alright, so, this talks about a
lot about measurements, how to
look at these different gases.
But, what else can we show, how can we
talk about how they're gonna function?
Well, the way that gases are behaving
has to do with something called Kinetic
Molecular Theory, which describes
exactly how they are going to work.
So I have some little, little,
little demonstrations I, I took from
a open online source to help show
you, see how, how do they function
so you can understand how these are
acting like little billiard balls.
So when we are looking at kinetic
molecular theory, This describes how
gases are in constant, random motion.
So they're just moving all over the place.
They are bouncing into all these
different things, going all over the
place, and they are constantly moving.
They don't stop.
Now, the second thing is...
These things are moving
in a straight line.
When they hit something,
they reflect and go back.
So they continuously keep moving.
They are like, if you have a pool table
and you have the little billiard balls,
they're bouncing all over the place.
They're not just stopping for anything.
So because of that, these
particles are really tiny.
There's a lot of empty
space in between them.
So they're always going to
be colliding and moving.
So when they collide,
Will they lose energy?
We assume that they don't.
That they are, they're like elastic.
They're like rubber.
When they hit, they, they bounce.
There's no energy being transferred.
So we like to think of
these as an ideal system.
Something that's easy
for us to study, to see.
Can we explain what we are
observing with our own eyes?
So when we are seeing that,
what that allows us to do is,
that energy is kinetic energy.
The energy of movement, right?
This is constant motion.
So because of that motion, That's
all related directly to temperature.
So we're going to try, I'm going to
show that to you, how that can be shown.
So how can we talk about
that in terms of collisions?
Well, the whole idea is that when you
have these different things, that the more
that the temperature's increasing, the
more that these are going to be colliding.
So if I show you my first example
here, and I have a little particle.
So I only have three particles.
They are slowly bouncing.
This is at room temperature.
So three little gas particles.
Bouncing around now, if I
start to heat it up, Oh, now
they're getting a lot of energy.
They're going to move faster and
a lot more, and they're going to
be colliding with all the walls
as they collide with the walls.
That's the pressure that we
are talking about, right?
They're confined to a specific volume.
We have five particles that are
here and they are continuously
going through this motion.
Now, if I take another example,
let's say I introduced 200 particles.
Not just five, but a lot of them.
On this one, the one thing that we're
going to be noticing is how much
collisions we're going to be having.
So, when I bring this up,
you're going to see that they're
colliding with each other.
They're colliding with the walls.
They are randomly going
in every single direction.
They are constantly hitting each other.
The walls, and when I start to heat it
up, it's like a free for all mayhem,
but they're not attaching to each other.
They're just bouncing
and continuously moving.
Now, even though it's really hot, what
happens if I start to cool it down and
go through that entire process where I
make it a little bit colder, right, with
the little ice cubes that are there?
Notice how they're slowing down.
They're less energy.
It's like a turtle moving.
And because of that, they almost start
to become like they're drifting in space,
which this is kind of how space behaves.
They're just particles floating around.
So, whether you're heating something up
or you're cooling it down, this is an
idea of how particles are exactly working.
Alright?
So, next time in the next video,
I'm going to be looking at how...
Do, uh, the different gas
laws, so we can go through the
mathematics of understanding.
But this was a simple, this was a short
video on how gases behave, how they work.
I hope this gave you an idea of
what to expect for your future
classes, and this has been Dr.
Dan.
Please consider hitting that
like and subscribe button.
I really appreciate all
your support, everybody.
I'll see y'all later.
Bye.